Guide to the Ernest Howe Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- California Mining, 1909-1932; Series I; 3.5; (9 boxes)
  - ROUND MOUNTAIN NEOCENE DRIFT PLACER MINE
    - Correspondence, 1919-23 (Box 6, Folder 74-82)
      See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 264
    - Agreements, incorporation, lease, 1919-23 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Financial statements, 1920-23 (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - WEST POINT MINES
    - Correspondence, 1919-22 (Box 6, Folder 85-90)
      See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 265
    - Correspondence, 1924-25 (Box 6, Folder 91)
    - Agreement to form syndicate, 1919 Oct 8 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Notes, outline, report on Keltz Group (EH), 1920 (Box 7, Folder 93)
    - "Notes on the Geology of the Lone Star, Read & Hillary, and Keltz Veins, West Point, Calaveras County, California," typescript and diagrams, 1922 Jan 9 (Box 7, Folder 94)
      See also: Oversize, Box 19, folder 279
    - "Notes on the Geology of the Lone Star, ...", background material, [1922] (Box 7, Folder 95)
    - Ore and bullion records, 1922 (Box 7, Folder 96)
    - Financial statements, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 97)
    - Maps
      See: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 266
  - GEOLOGICAL REPORTS ON NORTH STAR AND GRASS VALLEY
    - Geological Survey of the North Star Mine
      - "Report on the Geology of the North Star Mine," typescript and map (EH), 1910 (Box 7, Folder 98)
        See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 267
      - "Underground notes North Star Mine," notebook, 1910 (Box 7, Folder 99)
      - Ore and production notes, 1909-11, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 100)
        See also: Oversize, Box 19, folder 280
    - Geological Survey of the Champion Mines
      - "Report on the Geology of the Champion Mines," typescript (EH), 1911 Mar 29 (Box 7, Folder 101)
      - Notes, notebook, and map, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 102-04)
        See also: Oversize, Box 19, folder 281
      - "The Champion Mines Production 1893 to 1910," typescript, 1911 (Box 7, Folder 105)
    - North Star Mines history by William Hague, untitled typescript, 1913 May 25 (Box 7, Folder 106)
    - Cost data North Star and general, 1911-20, notes, [1913-20] (Box 7, Folder 107)
    - Reports on the Tightner Mine, typescripts, maps, and notes (EH), 1913-17 (Box 7, Folder 108)
      See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 268
    - The North Star Mines, Grass Valley, California, Statistical Statement for Visiting Members of the American Institute of Mining Engineers, 1915 Sep (Box 8, Folder 109)
    - Articles on North Star Mines from Mining and Scientific Press, 1914-15 (Box 8, Folder 110)
    - Journal containing a report on the geology of the Sierra Nevada, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 110a)
      Immediate Source of Acquisition
      Purchased from Charles Apfelbaum on the Arthur Corbitt Hoskins Memorial Fund, 2008.
    - Oriental mine report by Robert Bedford, typescript, maps, and correspondence, 1919-20 (Box 8, Folder 111)
      See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 269
    - X - Sultana - Daisy Hill mines, correspondence, map, and notes, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 112)
      See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 270
    - "Memorandum on the Vein Relations at Grass Valley. November 1921," typescript and maps, 1921 Dec 9 (Box 8, Folder 113)
      See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 271
    - Report on the Properties of the Banner Consolidated Mines, Inc., [1921?] (Box 8, Folder 114)
    - Statement of Howe's work for North Star Mines, [1921?] (Box 8, Folder 115)
    - "Notes on the Geology of the Rainbow Mine Alleghany, California," typescript (EH), 1922 Jan 15 (Box 8, Folder 116)
    - "The North Star Mines, Grass Valley - California, Notes on Development and Prospects," by Guy N. Bjorge, typescript and map, 1922 Oct (Box 8, Folder 117)
      See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 272
    - "Grass Valley Geology" (EH)
      - Typescript first draft and letter to Bedford, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 118)
      - Typescript/holograph second draft, [1922?] (Box 8, Folder 119)
      - Typescript third draft, [1922?] (Box 8, Folder 120)
    - Notes on petrography of North Star and New York Hill mines, 1922-23 (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - "The Gold Ores of Grass Valley, California" (EH)
      - Typescript first draft and notes, 1923 Jan-Feb (Box 8, Folder 122)
      - Typescript partial draft and notes, 1923 Mar-Oct (Box 8, Folder 123)
      - Typescript second draft, 1923 Sep 27 (Box 8, Folder 124)
      - Typescript third draft, 1924 Feb 27 (Box 8, Folder 125)
      - Typescript fourth draft, 1924 May 17 (Box 8, Folder 126)
      - Typescript fifth draft, [1924 May?] (Box 8, Folder 127)
      - Typescript sixth draft, [1924?] (Box 8, Folder 128)
      - Typescript seventh draft, [1924?] (Box 8, Folder 129)
      - Typescript eighth draft, [1924?] (Box 8, Folder 130)
    - "Wall Rocks and Ore Deposits North Star Mines" (EH)
      - Petrographic notes, 1923-24 (Box 9, Folder 131)
      - "Summary of Petrographic Notes", 1923 (Box 9, Folder 132)
      - Article in Mining and Scientific Press regarding Carson City Gold and Silver Mining Company v. North Star Mining Company
        See: Oversize, Box 19, folder 282
    - "Notes on Polished Specimens of North Star Ore," typescript (EH), 1924 Jan 22 (Box 9, Folder 133)
    - "Analysis of Deep Shaft Project of North Star Mines," by Robert Bedford, typescript, graphs, and maps, 1924 Mar (Box 9, Folder 134)
    - The Nevada City District Mines of Nevada County California in Relation to the Western Mines Consolidated, Inc., report by the president, A. D. Foote, [1925?] (Box 9, Folder 135)
    - Massachusetts Hill Mine development, report and correspondence, 1929 Jan (Box 9, Folder 136)
- Panama Canal Zone Geology, 1906-1908; Series II; 1; (2 boxes)
  The series documents Howe's service as geologist to the Isthmian Canal Commission. The material is organized into Howe's Report and Article, Correspondence and Notes, and Diagrams and Maps. Within each subseries material is arranged chronologically.
  - HOWE'S REPORT AND ARTICLE
    - "Preliminary Outline of Isthmian Geology", [1907] (Box 10, Folder 137)
    - [A Preliminary Report on the Geology of the Canal Zone], [pre-1907 Feb] (Box 10, Folder 138)
    - "A Preliminary Report on the Geology of the Canal Zone", 1907 Feb 4 (Box 10, Folder 139)
    - "Preliminary Report on the Geology of the Canal Zone", [1907 Feb] (Box 10, Folder 140)
    - "Geology of the Site of the Proposed Dam and Locks at Gatun," drafts, [1907 May] (Box 10, Folder 141)
    - "Final Report. Geology of Canal Zone", 1907 (Box 10, Folder 142)
    - "Report on the Geology of the Canal Zone", 1907 (Box 10, Folder 143)
    - "The Geology of the Isthmus of Panama," reprint from The American Journal of Science, vol. 26, 1908 Sep (Box 10, Folder 144)
  - CORRESPONDENCE AND NOTES
    - Correspondence, 1900-24, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 145-53)
    - Special Message of the President of the United States concerning the Panama Canal, 1906 (Box 10, Folder 154)
    - Index to notebooks (may refer to Howe's field notebooks, which are not in the collection), [1906] (Box 11, Folder 155)
    - Panama Canal clippings, 1906-14, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 156)
    - Notes on cement and seawater, [1906] (Box 11, Folder 157)
    - Notes on Panama Canal zone geology, 1906-07, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 158)
    - Notes on Panama Canal zone rocks collected in 1906, 1906-07 (Box 11, Folder 159)
    - Printed articles on Panama Canal, 1909, 1912 (Box 11, Folder 160)
    - Publications of the Isthmian Canal Commission, 1910, 1913 (Box 11, Folder 161)
    - References on Panama Canal zone geology, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 162)
    - Miscellaneous papers, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 163)
  - DIAGRAMS AND MAPS
    - Isthmian Canal Commission maps of the Canal Zone
      See: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 273
    - Geological cross sections of Panama canal zone, [1906-08] (Box 11, Folder 164)
    - Panama Canal relief map, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 165)
- Geological Projects, 1881-1930; Series III; 2; (5 boxes)
  This series contains a variety of material documenting Howe's professional career. Material is arranged chronologically. Reports or articles written by Howe are indicated by "(EH)" at the end the folder title.
  - 3 maps from U.S. surveys of west coast of North America, from Alaska to Washington Territory
    See: Oversize, Box 19, folder 283
  - Geological sketch of Newport; topographical map of Providence; street map of Harvard University; mineralogy notes
    See: Oversize, Box 19, folder 284
  - Illustrations (photoprints) for Geologic Atlas of the United States: Ouray Folio, Colorado. USGS, Dept. of Interior, [1898-1907] (Box 12, Folder 166)
  - United States Geological Survey correspondence, 1898-1910, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 167)
    See also: Box 10, folders 145-53
  - "Laccoliths," holograph article (EH), 1899 Apr 26 (Box 12, Folder 168)
  - "Types and Distribution of Rock Phosphates in the United States," holograph article for Geology, vol. 18, notes, and map (EH), 1899 May (Box 12, Folder 169)
    See also: Oversize, Box 19, folder 285
  - Howe's thesis notes, granite intrusions of Cascade, Oregon, 1900, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 170)
  - Petrographic Notes
    - Conglomerates and breccias (Box 12, Folder 171)
    - Gabbro, [1900] (Box 12, Folder 172)
    - Gabbros, basic dikes, Aminas Canyon, 1900 (Box 12, Folder 173)
    - Granites, pegmatites, aplites, granitic dikes, Aminas Canyon, 1900 (Box 12, Folder 174)
    - General petrography, [1900-15] (Box 12, Folder 175)
  - Engineer Mountain Survey, USGS, Colorado
    - "Notes on the Igneous Rocks of the Wichita and Arbuckle Mountains," typescripts (EH), [1901] (Box 12, Folder 176)
    - List of thin sections, 1900 (Box 13, Folder 177)
    - List of photographs of rock formations, 1901 (Box 13, Folder 178)
    - Notes, [1900-01] (Box 13, Folder 179)
  - Geological survey maps of California, South Dakota, and Wyoming with annotations
    See: Oversize, Box 19, folder 286
  - The Laccoliths of the Black Hills... with a Chapter on Experiments Illustrating Intrusion and Erosion, Dept. of the Interior - U.S. Geological Survey (EH), 1901 (Box 13, Folder 180)
  - "Recent Tuffs of the Soufière, St. Vincent"
    - Printed copy and typescript draft (EH), 1903 (Box 13, Folder 181)
    - Notes, [1903] (Box 13, Folder 182-83)
    - Photoprints, [1903] (Box 13, Folder 184)
    - Background material, 1903-12 (Box 13, Folder 185)
      See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 274
  - Review of A. Lacroix's La Montagne Pelée et ses Éruptions, typescript and notes (EH), 1905 (Box 13, Folder 186)
  - Photoprints of Hawaii and Vesuvius, [1905] (Box 13, Folder 187)
  - Geological bibliography, [1906] (Box 13, Folder 188-89)
  - Geological bibliography, [1906] (Box 14, Folder 190)
  - Muncey - Tuscarora coal properties
    - Reports on coal properties in Gunnison County, Colo., typescripts (EH), 1908-09 (Box 14, Folder 191-92)
    - Notes, [1889, 1908] (Box 14, Folder 193)
    - Correspondence, alphabetical by surname, 1908-10 (Box 14, Folder 194-95)
  - Landslides in the San Juan Mountains, Colorado, including a Consideration of their Causes and their Classification, Dept. of the Interior - U.S. Geological Survey (EH), 1901 (Box 14, Folder 196)
  - Holter Dam, Montana
    - Report on Geology at the Holter Dam Site, typescript (EH), 1910 (Box 14, Folder 197)
    - Correspondence, alphabetical by surname, 1910 (Box 14, Folder 198-200)
    - Field notes, 1910 (Box 14, Folder 201)
    - Photoprints, 1909-10 (Box 14, Folder 202)
    - Profile of dam, cross-section of rock layers; and data on the geologic units of Montana, [1910]
      See: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 275
  - "Report on Lands Belonging to Saint Luke's Hospital, Shenandoah County, Virginia and Hardy County, West Virginia," typescript and correspondence (EH), 1911 (Box 14, Folder 203)
  - "Landslides and the Sinking of Ground Above Mines," typescripts and correspondence (EH), 1913 (Box 14, Folder 204-05)
  - Review of report by the Royal Ontario Nickel Commission, typescript and notes (EH), 1913 (Box 14, Folder 206)
  - "Sudbury Ore Deposits"
    - Typescript first draft (EH), 1913 May 5 (Box 14, Folder 207)
    - "Sudbury Nickel deposits, general notes", [1913] (Box 14, Folder 208)
    - List of specimens, 1913 (Box 14, Folder 209)
    - Notes, [1913] (Box 15, Folder 210)
    - Background material, 1913-14 (Box 15, Folder 211)
    - Printed guide and maps, 1913 (Box 15, Folder 212)
      See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 276
  - Material on the refractive index of minerals
    See: Oversize, Box 19, folder 287
  - "Sulphide-bearing Rocks from Litchfield Connecticut," reprint, typescript, draft, and notes, 1915 (Box 15, Folder 213-15)
  - Geological survey maps of California
    See: Oversize, Box 19, folder 288
  - Ross Precision Computer promotional material, [1916-18] (Box 15, Folder 216)
  - Brazilian Expedition - Upper Amazon Region
    - "Rice Expedition 1916-1917, Amazon and Rio Negro, Brazil," typescript of Howe's original notes (EH), 1924 (Box 15, Folder 217)
    - "Amazon Geology," holograph article (EH), [1917] (Box 15, Folder 218)
    - Photoprints by W. T. Councilman, [1916-18] (Box 15, Folder 219)
    - Photoprints and postcards, [1916-17] (Box 15, Folder 220)
    - Weather journal, 1916-17 (Box 15, Folder 221)
    - Notes, [1916-17] (Box 15, Folder 222)
  - Amherst Meeting of the Geological Society of America, Paleontological Society, Mineralogical Society of America, and Society of Economic Geologists, program, letter, and photoprint, 1921 Dec (Box 15, Folder 223)
  - "Review of 'The Ore Magmas' - J. E. Spurr," typescript (EH), [1923] (Box 15, Folder 224)
  - Twin Vein Mining Company, Virginia, correspondence and map, 1924-25 (Box 16, Folder 225-26)
    See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 277
  - "Report on the Loring and Hague Lands, Houghton Michigan," by C. H. Baxter, correspondence, maps, and typescript, 1929-30 (Box 16, Folder 227)
    See also: Oversize, Broadsides, folder 278
  - Field notebook - Newport, R.I., n.d. (Box 16, Folder 228)
  - Profile of California from Cuyawa River to Kern River to Owens Lake
    See: Oversize, Box 19, folder 289
- Personal Papers, 1883-1931; Series IV; 0.75; (2 boxes)
  The papers in Series IV. are alphabetically arranged by heading. Miscellaneous papers have been placed at the end.
  - "The Aspen," by Ernest Howe in The Yale Courant, vol. 31, no. 10, 1895 Mar 23 (Box 17, Folder 229)
  - Correspondence, 1902-32 (Box 17, Folder 230)
  - Descendants of Louis Guion, printed genealogy, 1900 (Box 17, Folder 231)
  - Diary, 1907 (Box 17, Folder 232)
  - Diary, 1909 (Box 17, Folder 233)
  - Diary, 1911 (Box 17, Folder 234)
  - Diary, 1913 (Box 17, Folder 235)
  - Diary, 1915 (Box 17, Folder 236)
  - Diaries, 1920-22 (Box 17, Folder 237-39)
  - Diary, 1925 (Box 18, Folder 240)
  - Diaries, 1928-31 (Box 18, Folder 241-44)
  - Letters to Arnold Hague, 1915 (Box 18, Folder 245)
  - Newport Chapter, American Red Cross, notes from meetings, 1917 May (Box 18, Folder 246)
  - Newport Natural History Society, notes and correspondence, 1883-1915 (Box 18, Folder 247-50)
  - Notes on photographs taken at Grand Canyon, 1923 Mar 3 (Box 18, Folder 251)
  - Photoprints, 1911, [1919], n.d. (Box 18, Folder 252)
  - Miscellaneous, 1904, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 253)
- Oversize, 1881-1930; 5; (1 box, 25 broadside folders)
  Oversize contains oversize material from Series I, II, and III. The arrangement is based on the size of the material, but it also parallels the order of the collection.
  - SERIES I
    - North Star Mines Company
      - Correspondence, 1918-24 (Box BSD, folder 254)
      - Correspondence, 1918-24 (Box BSD, folder 255)
      - Correspondence, 1918-24 (Box BSD, folder 256)
      - Correspondence, 1918-24 (Box BSD, folder 257)
      - Correspondence, 1918-24 (Box BSD, folder 258)
      - Correspondence, 1918-24 (Box BSD, folder 259)
      - Correspondence, 1925-27 (Box BSD, folder 260)
      - Superintendent's-General managers monthly reports underground, 1918-19 (Box BSD, folder 261)
      - Superintendent's-General managers monthly reports underground, 1920, 1923 (Box BSD, folder 262)
      - Superintendent's-General managers monthly reports underground, 1927-29 (Box BSD, folder 263)
    - Round Mountain Neocene Drift Placer Mine
      - Correspondence, 1920-22 (Box BSD, folder 264)
    - West Point Mines
      - Correspondence, 1920-21 (Box BSD, folder 265)
      - Maps, 1919, n.d. (Box BSD, folder 266)
    - Geological Reports on North Star and Grass Valley
      - Geological Survey of the North Star Mine
        - "Report on the Geology of the North Star Mine," map (EH), [1910] (Box BSD, folder 267)
      - Reports on the Tightner Mine, maps (EH), 1913, n.d. (Box BSD, folder 268)
      - Oriental Mine report by Robert Bedford, maps, 1919 Nov 18 (Box BSD, folder 269)
      - X - Sultana - Daisy Hill mines, Daisy Hill data, map, [1919-20] (Box BSD, folder 270)
      - "Memorandum on the Vein Relations at Grass Valley. November 1921," maps, 1921-22 (Box BSD, folder 271)
      - "The North Star Mines, Grass Valley - California, Notes on Development and Prospects," by Guy N. Bjorge, map, 1922-23 (Box BSD, folder 272)
  - SERIES II.
    - Diagrams and Maps
      - Isthmian Canal Commission maps of the Canal Zone, 1905, 1907 (Box BSD, folder 273)
  - SERIES III.
    - "Recent Tuffs of the Soufière, St. Vincent," background material, 1903 (Box BSD, folder 274)
    - Holter Dam, Montana, Profile of dam; cross-section of rock layers, [1910] (Box BSD, folder 275)
    - "Sudbury Ore Deposits," printed maps, 1907-13 (Box BSD, folder 276)
    - Twin Vein Mining Company, Virginia, map (Box BSD, folder 277)
    - "Report on the Loring and Hague Lands, Houghton Michigan," by C. H. Baxter, maps, [1929] (Box BSD, folder 278)
  - SERIES I.
    - West Point Mines
      - "Notes on the Geology of the Lone Star, Read & Hillary, and Keltz Veins, West Point, Calaveras County, California," diagrams, 1922 Jan 7 (Box 19, Folder 279)
    - Geological Reports on North Star and Grass Valley
      - Geological Survey of the North Star Mine, table of production and tonnage, 1884-1911 (Box 19, Folder 280)
      - Geological Survey of the Champion Mines, map, [1911] (Box 19, Folder 281)
      - "Wall Rocks and Ore Deposits North Star Mines" (EH)
        - Article in Mining and Scientific Press regarding Carson City Gold and Silver Mining Company v. North Star Mining Company, 1896 Mar 28 (Box 19, Folder 282)
  - SERIES III.
    - 3 maps from U.S. surveys of west coast of North America, from Alaska to Washington Territory, 1881-85 (Box 19, Folder 283)
    - Geological sketch of Newport; topographical map of Providence; street map of Harvard University; mineralogy notes, 1897-98, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 284)
    - "Types and Distribution of Rock Phosphates in the United States," topographical map of Colorado, [1898-99] (Box 19, Folder 285)
    - Geological survey maps of California, South Dakota, and Wyoming with annotations, [1900] (Box 19, Folder 286)
    - Material on the refractive index of minerals, 1913-16 (Box 19, Folder 287)
    - Geological survey maps of California, [1916] (Box 19, Folder 288)
    - Profile of California from Cuyawa River to Kern River to Owens Lake, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 289)
- June 2006 Acquisition, 1893-1907; Series V; 0.42; (1 box)
  Notebooks and maps from Howe's 1906-1907 geological excursion to Panama.
  - Algebra notebook with enclosed Yale College material and photographs, 1893, undated (Box 20, Folder 290)
  - Map of Panama Canal region 1/50,000 Cristobal to Ahorca Lagarto, undated (Box 20, Folder 291)
  - Map of Panama Canal region 1/50,000 Ahorca Lagarto to Las Cascadades, undated (Box 20, Folder 292)
  - Map of Panama Canal region 1/50,000 Las Cascadades to La Boca and Naos Island, undated (Box 20, Folder 293)
  - Boring records and Bohio Dam site, 1906-1906 (Box 20, Folder 294)
  - Field notes, 1907-1907 (Box 20, Folder 295)
  - Panama notes and sketches, 1906-1906 (Box 20, Folder 296)
  - Panama notes, 1907-1907 (Box 20, Folder 297)
  - United States Geological Survey traverse notebook, undated (Box 20, Folder 298)